Guide to the Leonor Villegas de Magnón Papers
University of Houston Libraries
Leonor Villegas de Magnón Papers
1906-1982
04/2008-015
Villegas de Magnón, Leonor
3.50 linear feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
The papers of Leonor Villegas Magnón are organized into eight series: Correspondence, Biographical material, Publications/Manuscripts, Cruz Blanca documents, Texas and US history and politics, Women’s interests, Mexican history and politics, and Photographs.
Biographical Information:
Leonor Villegas de Magnón, daughter of Joaquín and Helosia Villegas, was born in Nuevo Laredo, Mexico on June 12, 1876. Educated at the Ursuline Convent in San Antonio and later the Academy of the Holy Cross in Austin, she received a teaching degree in 1895 from the Academy of Mount Saint Ursula in New York City. She married Adolfo Magnón, an American citizen, and the couple had three children, Leonor, Joaquín, and Adolfo. Leonor’s father left Mexico at the outbreak of the Mexican revolution, and when he died in 1910 the war prevented Leonor from returning to Mexico after his funeral. She stayed in Laredo, Texas where she opened a Kindergarten in her home.
Sympathetic to Francisco Madero and his opposition to the Díaz administration, Magnón, along with her friend Jovita Idar, wrote for La Crónica, a Laredo Spanish language newspaper published by Nicasio Idar. When war broke out again in Mexico in 1913 and Nuevo Laredo was attacked, Idar and Magnón crossed the Rio Grande to help nurse the wounded. Leonor then formed and financed La Cruz Blanca (the White Cross) to provide more organized medical assistance and medical supplies to wounded soldiers. Eventually she transformed her home, garage and school into a hospital for soldiers who crossed the border. Unfortunately, American army officials accused her of violating neutrality laws and took many of the soldiers into custody at Fort McIntosh. Leonor hired a lawyer in order to secure their release and after a time Secretary of State William Jennings Bryan ordered the state to comply. Later on, Leonor and twenty five other nurses joined Venustiano Carranza’s army and continued their work with La Cruz Blanca. She was awarded five medals for her work during the Revolution, and in the post war years continued her social and political activism. She opened a bilingual school for children in Laredo and founded a community action women’s organization, La unión de progreso, y caridad. She also worked for the State Democratic executive committee, Women’s Division of Texas in the 1930s. In the 1940s she returned to Mexico, where she was part of the Club internacional de mujeres, working for official recognition for the nurse veterans of the revolution. Eventually Leonor Villegas de Magnón returned to Laredo, where she died on April 17, 1955.
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Corporate Name:
La Cruz Blanca Nacional
Genre/Form of Material:
Books; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence; Manuscripts (document genre); Pamphlets; Periodicals; Photographs; Postcards
Personal Name:
Carranza, Venustiano, 1859-1920; Díaz, Porfirio, 1830-1915; Idar, Jovita, 1885-1946; Madero, Francisco I., 1873-1913; Magnón, Adolfo; Villa, Pancho, 1878-1923; Villegas de Magnón, Leonor
Topical Term:
Camp followers -- Mexico -- History; Mexico--History--Revolution, 1910-1920
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research.
Acquisition Information
Information of acquisition method not available.
Related Materials:
Photographs from the Leonor Villegas de Magnón Papers digital collection http://digital.lib.uh.edu/collection/ville
Scope and Contents
The papers of Leonor Villegas Magnón are organized into eight series: Correspondence, Biographical material, Publications/Manuscripts, Cruz Blanca documents, Texas and US history and politics, Women’s interests, Mexican history and politics, and Photographs. The collection contains correspondence, manuscripts and manuscript notes, personal biographical documents, and newspaper clippings. Of particular interest is information about La Cruz Blanca, La unión de progreso y caridad and her autobiographical novels La rebelde and The lady was a rebel. The collection contains material dating from 1906–1980.
Detailed List of Contents
- Correspondence
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains 34 folders, organized chronologically, with correspondence starting in 1913 and dated through 1980. The contained correspondence includes items from Leonor Magnón and documents related to her manuscripts sent by her relatives. Of particular interest is correspondence related to Magnón’s activities during the Mexican Revolution, including correspondence with Venustiano Carranza and other revolutionary leaders.
  - 1906-1913 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - January-March 1914 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - April 1914 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - May 1914 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - June 1914 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - July 1914 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - August-September 1914 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - October-December 1914 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1915 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1916 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1917-1918 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1919 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1920 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 1935-1938 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - 1941 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - 1942 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - 1943 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - 1950 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - 1951 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - 1952 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - 1953-1955 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - 1956 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - 1957-1959 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - 1960-1968 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - 1971-1973 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 1974 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 1978-1982 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Various Duplicates (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Personal Documents
  The 9 folders in this series include items dated from 1913–1948 and many undated documents. This series contains newspaper clippings, personal documents, deeds, and legal documents. See also: Series 8, photographs.
  - Address Book/Day Planner, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Newspaper Clippings (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous Saved Papers, Papers by Other Authors (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Diplomas, Certificates, Personal Documents (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Deeds (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Financial Ledger, 1945-1946 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Scrapbook Originals (Box 2, Folder 13-15)
- Publications/Manuscripts
  This series contains 19 folders with mostly undated manuscripts, writings, and publications authored by Leonor Villegas de Magnón. It includes her autobiographical works La Rebelde and The Lady was a Rebel and various publications in Laredo newspapers. See also: Series 8, photographs.
  - Writings - Texas/US History (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Writings - Mexican Revolution/History (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Writings - Literary/Political (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Writings - Cruz Blanca (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Manuscript-Related Documents - Notes on Photographs (Box 3, Folder 5-7)
  - Manuscript-Related Documents and Notes (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Manuscripts/Notes/Working Papers (Box 3, Folder 9-12)
  - Original Manuscript 1 - The Lady was a Rebel (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Original Manuscript 2 - The Lady was a Rebel (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Original Manuscript 3 - The Lady was a Rebel (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Complete Manuscript - The Lady was a Rebel (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Photocopy - The Lady was a Rebel Part 1 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Photocopy - The Lady was a Rebel Part 2 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Manuscript - La Rebelde (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Cruz Blanca Documents
  The 3 folders in this series contain mostly undated materials from the Cruz Blanca (White Cross) medical aid society founded by Leonor Villegas de Magnón during the Mexican Revolution. It contains a ledger, various newspaper clippings from Mexican and Texas newspapers, and other documents. See also: Series 8, photographs.
  - Cruz Blanca Ledger, 1914 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Cruz Blanca Miscellaneous Documents (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Newspaper Clippings (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Texas/US History and Politics
  The two folders in this series contain publications dated from 1913-1974 and undated newspaper clippings from various Texas and US publications.
  - Newspaper Clippings (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Books/Magazines/Pamphlets (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Women’s Interests
  The 3 folders in this series contain newspaper clippings, books, and pamphlets dating from 1912 to 1974, with many undated materials. Of particular interest is a book about the history of Texas women, and the documents relating to the women’s societies: La unión de progreso y caridad (the union of progress and charity) and La agrupación auxiliar femenina de voluntarias para la defensa nacional (the women’s auxiliary of volunteers for the national defense). Also included is information about the Pan American Roundtable.
  - La sociedad de “Union, progreso y caridad” de Laredo (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Agrupación Aux. femenina de voluntarias para la defense nacional (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Newspaper Clippings and Documents (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Mexican History and Politics
  The 5 folders in this series contain newspaper clippings, artistic programs, books, magazines, and pamphlets dating from 1912 to 1974, with some undated materials. The documents particularly emphasize the Mexican Revolution. See also: Series 8, photographs.
  - Newspaper Clippings and Other Documents (Box 6, Folder 9-10)
  - Programs, Artistic Events (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Books/Magazines/Pamphlets (Box 6, Folder 12-13)
- Photographs
  The 10 folders in this series contain photographs maintained by Leonor Villegas de Magnón. Many of these photographs are related to her autobiographical novel La Rebelde and her participation in the Mexican Revolution. Of special note are photographs of Venustiano Carranza, Francisco Madero, and photographs of the members of La Cruz Blanca. Other photographs feature generals and soldiers of the Mexican Revolution and the family and friends of Villegas de Magnón. The photographs are organized thematically.
  - Leonor Villegas de Magnón Personal Photographs (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - From left to right: Leonor Villegas de Magnón, Guillermo Martínez Celis, and Aracelito García. Back of the picture: Mayor Guillermo M. Celis, Aracelito y la Rebelde. Postcard. (Box 7, Folder 1, Item 1)
    - Panoramic picture. Sitting in the train Leonor Villegas de Magnón. Caption: Banda del Gral. Murguía. Charcas. Jul 16, 1914. Fot. E. Montoya de la C. B. Nacional (Box 7, Folder 1, Item 2)
    - Close-up of Item 2 (Box 7, Folder 1, Item 3)
    - Picture of two couples. From left to right: Leonor Villegas de Magnón, Adolfo Magnón, Lily Long. Back of the picture: Pedro Garrino Parroquia (Box 7, Folder 1, Item 4)
    - Adolfo Magnón, Leonor Villegas de Magnón, Mrs. Lily Long (Box 7, Folder 1, Item 5)
    - Group Photo. Second row third from Left: Leonor Villegas de Magnón. (Box 7, Folder 1, Item 6)
    - Group photo. Third from left: Leonor Villegas de Magnón (Box 7, Folder 1, Item 7)
    - Villegas family home. Caption: Villegas home Cor. Salinas + Victoria (Back: Brewster home, Houston and Main) (Box 7, Folder 1, Item 8)
    - Leonor Villegas de Magnón, Lilly Long and officer (Box 7, Folder 1, Item 9)
    - Leonor presenting a document (Box 7, Folder 1, Item 10)
    - Leonor Villegas de Magnón, Leonor Grubbs (daughter) and Leonor Smith (granddaughter) (Box 7, Folder 1, Item 11)
    - Leonor and friends at Mr. St. Ursula’s Convent, NY (1894) (Box 7, Folder 1, Item 12)
    - Contents of Pancho Villa and Leonor Villegas Magnón’s carved box (Box 7, Folder 1, Item 13)
    - Leonor Villegas de Magnón in front of a mirror, 1895 (Box 7, Folder 1, Item 14)
    - Jan 1901, Wedding Photo, Adolfo Magnón and Leonor Villegas (Box 7, Folder 1, Item 15)
  - Cruz Blanca Photographs (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Cruz Blanca leaving El Paso for Ciudad Juarez (Box 7, Folder 2, Item 1)
    - Group photo of La Cruz Blanca members, center: Leonor Villegas de Magnón (Box 7, Folder 2, Item 2)
    - Leonor Villegas de Magnón and Maria Villarreal visit the family of a fallen soldier. (Box 7, Folder 2, Item 3)
    - Leonor with La Cruz Blanca members at Saucito Pantheon Cemetery, San Luis Potosi (Box 7, Folder 2, Item 4)
    - Leonor and ladies of Cruz Blanca 1st brigade (Box 7, Folder 2, Item 5)
    - Cruz Blanca National organizing hospital in Monterrey (Box 7, Folder 2, Item 6)
    - Leonor and Aracelito Garcia with flag of La Cruz Blanca, 1914 (Box 7, Folder 2, Item 7)
    - Leonor and Aracelito Garcia with flag of La Cruz Blanca, 1914 (Box 7, Folder 2, Item 8)
    - Leonor, Gentleman and ladies of the Cruz Blanca (back: Los c. Generales… see Folder 7, Item 1) (Box 7, Folder 2, Item 9)
    - Group photo of La Cruz Blanca members, center: Leonor Villegas de Magnón, series of signatures on back. (Box 7, Folder 2, Item 10)
    - Nurses of La Cruz Blanca and 2 gentlemen ( From Left to right the nurses are, Margarita Alonso, Elvira Idar, Panchita Ruiz, Angelita Esparza, Leonor Villegas de Magnón, Catalina Guervara, Nena Magnón (Leonor Grubbs), José Ugarte, and Editor of El Progreso (Leonor’s home) (Box 7, Folder 2, Item 11)
    - Leonor, Ladies and gentlemen of Cruz Blanca, June 28, 1914 (Box 7, Folder 2, Item 12)
  - Venustiano Carranza Photographs (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - General Páufilo Nátera greets Venustiano Carranza (Box 7, Folder 3, Item 1)
    - Venustiano Carranza and Pablo González. El C. Pr. Jefe V. Carranza y el Gral. En Jefe P. Gonzalez. Después de la comida. La Cañada Qtaro. 1º 21. 916 (Box 7, Folder 3, Item 2)
    - Mariano Arieta, Venustiano Carranza (Box 7, Folder 3, Item 3)
    - Signed portrait of Venustiano Carranza. Caption: A mi buen amiga y patriota correligionaria, Sra. Leonor Villegas de Magnón. V. Carranza. México Agosto 8 de 1916 (Box 7, Folder 3, Item 4)
    - Group photo. Venustiano Carranza. Caption: Fot. E. M. de la G. B. Nacional (Box 7, Folder 3, Item 5)
    - Group Photo. Venustiano Carranza. Caption: El primer jefe del Ejército Constitucionalista, en Cananea. No 67. Abitia. Back of the postcard: Continuándose el movimiento de una manera prodigiosa. En estos días se emprenderá el avance hacia el centro de la República. Todo camina perfectamente. El General Obregón ya se está movilizando con bastantes fuerzas. Muy pronto tendré el gusto de saludarlo personalmente. Favor de escribirme. Nogales a 11 de XXX de 1914. (Box 7, Folder 3, Item 6)
    - Group Photo. Venustiano Carranza. Back of the postcard: Sánchez Azcona hablándole al pueblo de Santa Ana al pasar para Carranza. (Box 7, Folder 3, Item 7)
    - Group Photo. Venustiano Carranza. Caption: La Junta Revolucionaria. (Box 7, Folder 3, Item 8)
    - Group Photo, people eating. Far left: Venustiano Carranza, from right: Felipe González (Box 7, Folder 3, Item 9)
    - Group photo. Venustiano Carranza. Back of postcard: Luis Cabrera addressing Carranza – behind him, Isidro Fabela next Peraldi Carranza’s nephew and private secretary (Box 7, Folder 3, Item 10)
    - Group photo. First to the left: Jesús Carranza. Third from the left: Leonor Villegas de Magnón. Fourth from the left: Venustiano Carranza. Eight from the left: Gral. Pablo González (Box 7, Folder 3, Item 11)
    - Group photo. At the center: Venustiano Carranza (Box 7, Folder 3, Item 12)
    - Group photo. Revolutionary militia. Center walking: Venustiano Carranza. Back of postcard: Los señores Carranza y Maytorena y General Felipe Ángeles momentos en que tomaban el cowboy para dirigirse de Nabojoa a San Blaz, Sin. El 18 de enero de 1914 (Box 7, Folder 3, Item 13)
    - Group of generals. Caption: Los Grales. Blanco y Hay antes de conferenciar con el Primer Jefe V. Carranza en Teoloyucan. Agosto-1914. Fot. E. Montoya (Box 7, Folder 3, Item 14)
    - Group photo. Center, looking to the camera: Venustiano Carranza. Back of the picture: Isidro Fábula. Felicitos Villarreal. El Primer Jefe. (Box 7, Folder 3, Item 15)
    - Group Photo. Fourth from right: Venustiano Carranza. Caption: El primer Jefe en su visita al Desierto de los Leones. Sep. 1914. Fot E. Montoya. Photo of Venustiano Carranza (Left) and General José María Maytorena. Back of the picture: Don Venustiano. Gral. Maytorena. (Box 7, Folder 3, Item 16)
    - Lilly Long, Leonor Villegas de Magnón, Venustiano Carranza (Box 7, Folder 3, Item 17)
    - From left to right: I. Caballero, T. Manzo, P. Gonzalez, Venustiano Carranza, Carrera Torres. (Box 7, Folder 3, Item 18)
    - From right to left: Felipe Angeles, Gobernador del Estado José M. Maytorena, Venustiano Carranza and Lucio Blanco. Caption: El C. Primer Jefe don Venustiano Carranza, el Señor Gobernador del Estado Don José M. Maytorena y los generales Felipe Angeles y Lucio Blanco, en momentos de presenciar las maniobras militares que tuvieron verificativo en la Calzada del Centenario, el 15 de Diciembre de 1913. Rodriguez Photo. (Box 7, Folder 3, Item 19)
    - Photo of Venustiano Carranza (Left) and General José María Maytorena. Back of the picture: Don Venustiano. Gral. Maytorena. (Box 7, Folder 3, Item 20)
    - Photos of Madero and Carranza in tailor propaganda. Postcard (Box 7, Folder 3, Item 21)
    - Group photo with Venustiano Carranza (Box 7, Folder 3, Item 22)
    - Signed portrait of Venustiano Carranza. Caption: A mi buen amiga y patriota correligionaria, Sra. Leonor Villegas de Magnón. V. Carranza. México Agosto 8 de 1916 (Box 7, Folder 3, Item 23)
    - Gathering, Leonor, Venustiano Carranza, children, Sra. De Pastor Romizy, Isidro Faset, General Pesquiera, Panino Juntes, Constitutionalist officers and nurses (Box 7, Folder 3, Item 24)
  - General Pablo González Photographs (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - General Pablo González. Back: General Pablo González. This photograph was made at C. Victoria just after the capture. Back of the picture: General Pablo Gonzalez. This photograph was made at C. Victoria just after the capture (Box 7, Folder 4, Item 1)
    - General Pablo Gonzalez signed picture. (Box 7, Folder 4, Item 2)
    - Group Photo. Caption: El C. Grl. En jefe P. Gonzalez, en el Teatro Mexicano. Febrero 5. 1916. J. Mora. 312. Back of the picture: Gral. P. González. A. Breceda. (Box 7, Folder 4, Item 3)
    - Group Photo. Caption: El Gral. P. González. En el Teatro Mexicano. Febrero 5. 1916. J. Mora (Box 7, Folder 4, Item 4)
    - Group photo. Pablo González with two unidentified women. Caption: El C. Grl. en jefe P. González entre las familias de las avanzadas adelante de Chalco. 1.18.916. J. Mora. 271 (Box 7, Folder 4, Item 5)
    - Field photo. Caption: La infantería hace un movimiento embolbente (sic). Orden del C. Gral. En J. P. González. Tetelco 2.8.916. J. Mora 322 (Box 7, Folder 4, Item 6)
    - Group Photo. Grals. Dávila y Pablo González y Coronel P. de la Graza. Caption: Grals. Dávila y González y Coronel P. de la Garza en la Estación de Saltillo, Julio 15-1914 (Box 7, Folder 4, Item 7)
    - Group Photo. Generales Pablo González y Luis Gutiérrez. Caption: Grales. P. González y L. Gutiérrez observando el desembarque de la artillería Venado S.L.P. Jul. 18-1914. Fot. E. Montoya de la C.B. Nacional. Back of the picture: X Eulalio Gutiérrez Gobernador de San Luis Potosí. XX Col. Federico Mémdes – artillero. (Box 7, Folder 4, Item 8)
    - Group photo. Caption: El C. Grl. jefe P. González en el panteón de S. Fernando. Febrero 5 de 1916. J. Mora. 309 (Box 7, Folder 4, Item 9)
    - Caption: El C. Grl. El jefe P. González en la oficina de telégrafo delante de Chalco. 1.18.916. J. Mora. 240 (Box 7, Folder 4, Item 10)
    - Gral. Pablo González. Caption: J. Mora. 244. El C. Grl. P. González en su casa particular. Habla con rl. M. W. Gonzalez. Mixcoac.1.20.916. Back of the picture: Gral. Castillo Tapia Orator (Box 7, Folder 4, Item 11)
    - Signed portrait of Pablo González. Caption: A la señora Presidenta de la Cruz Blanca de Laredo, Tex. H. Matamoros Tamps. 2/2-914. El general (Box 7, Folder 4, Item 12)
  - Francisco I. Madero Photographs (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Postcard. Group Photo. Caption: Prop. Asegurada. Back of the picture: Don Francisco Madero. (Box 7, Folder 5, Item 1)
    - Postcard. Francisco I. Madero and Victoriano Huerta. Caption: Madero en el balcón central de la fotografía Daguerre. Back of the picture: Madero and Huerta. (Box 7, Folder 5, Item 2)
    - Postcard. Group Photo. Francisco I. Madero. Caption: Prop. Asegurada. Back of the picture: F. Madero entering underground protection. Mexico City. (Box 7, Folder 5, Item 3)
    - Madero’s father’s house, annihilated by bombardment. Landscape (Box 7, Folder 5, Item 4)
    - Francisco I. Madero on a horse. Caption: Madero ovacionado por el pueblo. Mexico, 9, Febro. 1913. postcard (Box 7, Folder 5, Item 5)
    - Portrait of Francisco I. Madero sitting on a chair. Postcard (Box 7, Folder 5, Item 6)
    - Postcard. Multitude and Madero. Caption: El Señor Pte. Llegando a palacio el día de Feb. 1913. (Box 7, Folder 5, Item 7)
    - Madero’s house. Caption: Residencia del ex-presidente Madero. Incendiada el 11 de Fec, 1913. No 36. H. J. Gutiérrez Photo. (Box 7, Folder 5, Item 8)
    - Postcard. Portrait. Left: Aquiles Serdán. Right: Francisco I. Madero (Box 7, Folder 5, Item 9)
    - Group photo. Center: Francisco Madero. Postcard (Box 7, Folder 5, Item 10)
    - Photo: Padre Hidalgo, Benito Juarez and Francisco Madero, Caption: Trilogía Mexicana (Box 7, Folder 5, Item 11)
    - Portrait Francisco I Madero. Inscription in photo: Patria – Lealtad – Justicia – Democracia. El presidente Francisco I Madero (Box 7, Folder 5, Item 12)
  - Identified Photographs (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Right: General Cándido Aguilar (Box 7, Folder 6, Item 1)
    - A couple horseback riding. Caption: Gral. Miguel Aleman. Back of the picture: Ma. del Carmen Rubio de La Llave. Dedico este retrato con mi estimado jefe. Ya recibió su grado de Gral. Miguel. Alemán a mi querida jefa Sra. Leonor Villegas de Magnón. Junio/2/1914. Saltillo. Picture is attached to paper that reads: Marietta. Carmen Rubio de la Llave. “La Marieta” from Veracruz joined forces with Gen. Alemán when she was 18 yrs. Held rank of coronela (Box 7, Folder 6, Item 2)
    - Back of the picture: Contains picture of Ignacio Belendez. Mary Goodson’s Grand-father. Figura en la historia de México por su acción heróica durante el gobierno de Juárez. (Box 7, Folder 6, Item 3)
    - Group photo. Back of the picture: Gral. Lucio Blanco y jefes constitucionalistas en Matamoros Tam. X Lucio Blanco, XX Cesario Castro, XXX General Francisco Artigas. (Box 7, Folder 6, Item 4)
    - Group Photo. Back of the picture: This is General Caballero, governor of Tamaulipas. He is here in this hotel, March 23, 1918 (Box 7, Folder 6, Item 5)
    - Postcard. Gral. Luis G. Caballero. Caption: Gral. Luis G. Caballero No. 131. H. J. Gutiérrez. Foto es prop. México. (Box 7, Folder 6, Item 6)
    - Portrait. Caption: Gral. Luis Caballero. Obsequio a la Señora Leonor Villegas de Mañon. Nuevo Laredo, Tamps. Enero 10 de 1917. Signed: El general Luis Caballero. (Box 7, Folder 6, Item 7)
    - Portrait of General Juan G. Cabral. Caption: General G. Cabral (Box 7, Folder 6, Item 8)
    - Postcard. Group photo. N.17. Después de la protesta del presidente Lic. F. Carbajal. H. J. Gutiérrez foto. Es prop. México. (Box 7, Folder 6, Item 9)
    - Group photo. José Carranza. Caption: Gral. J. Carranza y Estado Mayor. (Box 7, Folder 6, Item 10)
    - Group photo. Jesús Carranza. Caption: Gral. Jesús Carranza. Saltillo. Postcard. (Box 7, Folder 6, Item 11)
    - Group photo. Caption: Ing. Castillo Tapia proclamando un discurso en el Palacio de Gbno. de S.L. Potosí el día de la protesta del C. Gbdor. Eulalio Gutiérrez. Julio 21 de 1914. Fot. E. Montoya de la G. B. Postcard. (Box 7, Folder 6, Item 12)